Guide to the Stephen Harrigan Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Stephen Harrigan Papers
1971-2000
The Wittliff Collections
Harrigan, Stephen, 1948-
SWWC.012
17.5 Linear Feet
35 boxes Plus oversize.
The collection is composed of 21 boxes of manuscripts, galley proofs, notes, clippings, correspondence, artwork, financial and legal papers, screenplays, photographs and artifacts, spanning from 1971 to 2000, that document Stephen Harrigan's writing career.
Scope and Contents
The collection is composed of 21 boxes of manuscripts, galley proofs, notes, clippings, correspondence, artwork, financial and legal papers, screenplays, photographs, and artifacts, from 1971 to 2000 that document Stephen Harrigan's writing career. It has been arranged into six series: Works (1971-2000, undated), Correspondence (1976-1991, undated), Personal Materials (undated), Works by Other Authors, (1971-1972, 1992-1993, undated), Texas Institute of Letters (1982-1983, 1985-1986), and Clippings (1971-1983).
The Works series comprises the largest part of the Harrigan collection. It thoroughly documents Harrigan's methodical writing process. Most of the books and articles can be traced from the earliest notes taken by Harrigan to a proof copy or published work. The other series relate generally to his writing career. The materials are arranged in chronological order. Largely absent from the collection are personal papers or correspondence.
Books in the Stephen Harrigan Collection have been cataloged separately.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Stephen Harrigan and Bill Wittliff beginning in 1987. Contact the The Wittliff Collections for information about additional materials from this writer that have not yet been fully processed.
Biographical Notes
Stephen Harrigan was born on October 5, 1948, and grew up in Oklahoma City, Abilene and Corpus Christi. After receiving a degree in English from The University of Texas at Austin in 1971, Harrigan briefly attended graduate school and worked as a yardman and as an ad writer for the University Co-op. He contributed articles to a number of magazines, including Rolling Stone, The Atlantic Monthly, Esquire and The Texas Observer. He became a regular writer for Texas Monthly shortly after its inception and co-founded and edited Lucille, a journal of poetry, which published 10 issues between 1974 and 1978.
Harrigan received a Dobie-Paisano fellowship in 1977, which allowed him to complete his first novel. Aransas, published by Knopf in 1980, tells the story of Jeff Dowling, an alienated young man who comes to terms with himself and the world as he trains two dolphins for a circus in Port Aransas, Texas. The New York Times named the novel one of the notable books of 1980, and reviewers praised its realism and style. His second novel, Jacob's Well, also focused on man's relationship with nature, following the lives of three people who are drawn together to explore an artesian well in Central Texas. The book was named one of the best books of 1984 by The Washington Post and The Dallas Morning News.
Harrigan's recent books, until the publication in 2000 of Gates of the Alamo, have been nonfiction. As a freelance writer and later staff writer and editor for Texas Monthly, Harrigan displayed a talent for journalism, contributing interviews and other investigative pieces, but he also focused on the natural environment, writing about rivers, Big Bend, Padre Island and other Texas landmarks. Many of these essays were collected in Harrigan's third book, A Natural State: Essays on Texas (1988), which was recently republished by the University of Texas Press. His 1992 book Water and Light: A Diver's Journey to a Coral Reef combined research on aquatic life with his own experiences scuba diving off a coral reef in the Caribbean. The New York Times Book Review called Water and Light "moving, intelligent ... literary," and praised Harrigan's "remarkable ability to discuss the metaphysical and spiritual aspects of underwater exploration." Harrigan has also published a book of poetry and written screenplays, one of which, The Last of His Tribe, was broadcast on HBO.
Harrigan's works are characterized by an intense interest in humans and their relationship to the environment around them. He once wrote of his interest in natural subjects: "I don't know what nature is exactly--whether it is a category that includes human beings or shuts them out--but for me it has always contained that hint of eeriness, the sense that some vital information--common knowledge to all the universe--has been specifically withheld from me. Sometimes, as with the snake, this secrecy has seemed malevolent, but far more often it has been wonderfully tantalizing. For much of my life I have been obsessed with nature, but not in the way a naturalist would be obsessed with it--driven to classify, to define relationships, to comprehend the world's marvelous intricacy. I have simply wanted to feel more fully a part of that intricacy, to see something other than neutral scorn in the eyes of that half-imagined snake." (Introduction to A Natural State, UT Press, 1994)
Harrigan lives in Austin with his wife Sue Ellen and three daughters.
Authors, American -- Texas -- 20th century; Journalism -- Texas; Screenwriters -- United States; Historians -- Texas; Texas -- Description and travel; Natural history literature; Harrigan, Stephen, 1948-
- Works, 1971-2000, undated
  Series Description
  This series surveys Harrigan's creative works from his work as ad writer at the University Co-op to the publication of his book, Water and Light. It includes manuscript drafts, notes, notebooks, galley proofs, correspondence, magazines, clippings, financial and legal papers, screenplays, photographs and artifacts. In some cases Harrigan added notes and inscriptions describing the materials and providing background information. This series is further divided into six subseries: Early Works, Books, Screenplays, Songs, Contributions to Texas Monthly, and General Works.
  The first subseries, Early Works, contains notes, clippings, manuscripts, correspondence, artwork, financial papers and forms documenting Harrigan's writing before the publication of his first book. It contains clippings of the ads Harrigan wrote for the University Co-op and materials from Lucille, the journal of poetry that he helped found and edit. Both are introduced by notes written by Harrigan in 1988 giving additional information and background about his job at the Co-op and his association with Lucille. The Co-op clippings are arranged chronologically, and the Lucille files have been grouped by type of material, having lost their original order. Of particular interest in the Lucille files are the three folders of submissions of aspiring poets, some of whom have gone on to literary success, such as Naomi Shihab (Nye), R. S. Gwynn and Vassar Miller.
  The second subseries, entitled Books, contains research notes, background materials, legal papers, handwritten and typed manuscripts, galley proofs, correspondence, reviews and artwork for four of Harrigan's published books. There are multiple drafts of each book, and the handwritten notes and early drafts of Aransas, Jacob's Well, Water and Light and Gates of the Alamo provide an overview of Harrigan's writing process. His attention to detail and in-depth organization are demonstrated in his research for Water and Light, which includes two boxes of index cards with notes about the sea and the history of diving as well as his personal notes from his trip to Grand Turk Island. The materials are arranged alphabetically by book.
  Screenplays, the third subseries, contains research notes and multiple drafts of Harrigan's screenplay ISHI, which was filmed for HBO in 1992 as The Last of His Tribe. Many of these drafts were maintained in notebooks and materials found in the pockets of these notebooks have been placed at the back of each folder. The drafts are arranged chronologically, from the earliest draft to the final production script and shooting notes. Also found in the subseries is the script "Moonwalker," co-written by Harrigan and Lawrence Wright.
  The fourth subseries, Songs, contains various typed and handwritten drafts of a song written by Harrigan entitled "The Old Three."
  The fifth subseries, Contributions to Texas Monthly, contains research materials and notes, manuscript drafts, galley proofs, correspondence, photographs, artwork, and published articles written by Harrigan for Texas Monthly magazine. Harrigan's talent as a journalist is well documented here, showing the broad range of his interests, from an interview with Governor Bill Clements to research on the sculptor Pompio Coppini to essays on the natural wonders of Texas. Some of these articles were later published in Harrigan's third book, A Natural State: Essays on Texas. Also included are a number of complete issues of Texas Monthly in which Harrigan's articles appeared.
  Within the final subseries are general materials relating to Harrigan's writing career. It includes multiple handwritten and typed drafts on broadcasting, a typed essay on the exploration of Texas, an application for the NASA "Journalist in Space" program, a press release, and a clipping about the author. Also included are handwritten notebooks of Harrigan's poetry and prose.
  - Early Works, 1971-1978, undated
    - Co-op Clippings, 1971-1974, undated
      - Note by Harrigan concerning his time at the Co-op, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Ads, March 1971 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Ads, April 1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Ads, January 1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - Ads, May 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - Ads, November 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Ads, December 1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Ads, January 1973 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Ads, February 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Ads, March 1973 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Ads, April 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Ads, May 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Ads, June 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Ads, July 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Ads, August 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Ads, September 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - Ads, October 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Ads, November 1973 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - Ads, December 1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Ads, January 1974 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Ads, February 1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      - Ads, March 1974 (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Ads, April 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - Ads, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Lucille, 1972-1978, undated
      - Note by Harrigan concerning his time running the magazine, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - 2 Submissions for publication and correspondence, includes copy of MFA thesis by R. S. Gwynn entitled "After the Nigerian Air Show, Poems by R.S. Gwynn," University of Arkansas, and correspondence with Gunnar Hansen, 1972, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Submissions for publication and correspondence, includes poems by and correspondence from Vassar Miller (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Submissions for publication and correspondence (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Design notes, photos and sketches (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - 7 Financial papers, includes bank statements and cancelled checks (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - 8 Grant applications, guidelines and correspondence, 1974-1977, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Reviews, 1975-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Empty file folders, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Books, 1977-2000, undated
    - Aransas, 1977-1980, undated
      - Dobie-Paisano Application and acceptance letter (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - 2 Correspondence and contract for publication of Aransas (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Notes and notebook 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Notebooks 2 and 3, 1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Notebooks 4 and 5, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Notebooks 6 and 7, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Notebooks 8 and 9, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Revisions, two notebooks, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Original typescript, contains deleted first chapter, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
      - Early typescript, bound, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Edited typescript, International Creative Management's copy, undated (Box 4, Folder 4, Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Typescript with typesetting notes, 1980 (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Various chapters with typesetting notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence regarding revisions from Alfred A. Knopf Publishing (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - First proof with handwritten revisions, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Page proofs (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - Final page proofs (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Reviews, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6, Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Screenplay of Aransas by Robert Lovenheim, includes correspondence, 1980, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Jacob's Well, 1981-1984, undated
      - Notes and maps, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Notebooks 1 and 2, 1981, undated (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - Notebooks 3 and 4, undated (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Notebook, no number (begins with Chapter 4 notes), 1983 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - Original manuscript with corrections, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 2-4)
      - Early draft with changes, undated (Box 6, Folder 5-6, Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Early draft, undated (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
      - Author's galleys, undated (Box 7, Folder 5)
      - Reviews, 1984, undated (Box 7, Folder 6, Box 19, Folder 2)
      - Publicity, includes Simon Schuster Catalog and book signing invitations, 1983, undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
      - Correspondence, 1982, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Screenplay agreement between Stephen Harrigan and Ron Coley, 1984 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Sleepyhead, undated
      - Published book of poetry, drafts of poems, and extra poems not included in the book (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Water and Light, 1987-1992, undated
      - Trip to Turks and Caicos Islands, notes, map, sketches, 1987, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Research notes, general outline of chapters (Box 8, Folder 2)
      - Prospectus and sample chapter with handwritten notes (Box 8, Folder 3)
      - Typescript of draft, includes correspondence with Houghton Mifflin Publishing Company (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
      - Edited manuscript copy with style sheet, undated (Box 8, Folder 6-7)
      - Typescript with editor's notes, undated (Box 8, Folder 8, Box 9, Folder 1)
      - Edited master proofs, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 2)
      - Author's marked set with cover, 1992, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
      - Author's extra set, 1992, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence, 1991-1992, undated (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - Publicity, Houghton Mifflin catalog and mail-outs, 1992, undated (Box 19, Folder 7)
      - Audiotapes, undated (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Comanche Midnight & Other Essays, undated
      - Typescript, undated (Box 20, Folder 1-2)
      - Bound typescript, undated (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Gates of the Alamo, 1987, 2000, undated
      - Correspondence (letter from Harrigan to John Sterling, Editor in Chief, Houghton Mifflin. The book was contracted with Houghton Mifflin, but moved with John Sterling to Broadway Books/Knopf.), April 12, 1987 (Box 20, Folder 4)
      - Research note-cards, Set 1(A-I) (Box 21)
      - Research note-cards, Set 2 (J-S) (Box 22)
      - Research note-cards, Set 3 (S-Z and miscellaneous) (Box 23)
      - Chapter notes and research, undated (Box 24, Folder 1-2)
      - Costume notes, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Typescript with notes by Elizabeth Crook, undated (Box 24, Folder 4-5, Box 25, Folder 1-3)
      - Typescript with notes by Hardin, undated (Box 25, Folder 4-5, Box 26, Folder 1-3)
      - Typescript with notes by Huffines, undated (Box 26, Folder 4-5, Box 27, Folder 1-3)
      - Typescript with notes by David Lindley, undated (Box 27, Folder 4, Box 28, Folder 1-2)
      - Bound typescript draft, sent to International Creative Management, undated (Box 28, Folder 3-4, Box 29, Folder 1-2)
      - Typescript, undated (Box 29, Folder 3, Box 30, Folder 1-2)
      - Publicity, Alfred A. Knopf catalog, Spring 2000 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Screenplays, 1986-1991, undated
    - ISHI, 1986-1987, 1990-1991
      - Research, notes, clippings, 1986, 1991, undated (Box 31, Folder 1)
      - Research notebooks and note-cards, undated (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - First draft, December 1987 (Box 10, Folder 1)
      - First draft (copy), December 1987 (Box 10, Folder 2)
      - Second draft, includes correspondence with Texas Monthly Publishing, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
      - Draft that Harrigan says got him invited to the Sundance Film Festival, also labeled second draft, undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
      - Third draft, September 1990 (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - First HBO Draft (Take One), August 1990 (Box 10, Folder 6)
      - First HBO Draft (Submitted), September 1990 (Box 10, Folder 7)
      - Draft, December 6, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      - Draft, December 20, 1990 (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - Drafts, January 1991 (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
      - Draft, February 3, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - Draft, February 21, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - Draft, March 30, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - Draft, August 14, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Annotated draft, August 29, 1991 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - Draft, September 6, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Production draft with revisions, September 10, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Production file, includes script, staff and crew information, shooting schedule, and notes, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Movie prop, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Moonwalker, undated
      - Script by Lawrence Wright and Stephen Harrigan, undated (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Songs, undated
    - "The Old Three," typed draft with corrections (Box 31, Folder 3)
  - Contributions to Texas Monthly, 1978-1992, undated
    - Texas Monthly Articles, 1978-1988, undated
      - "Coppini the Great," research file, photographs, and correspondence, 1984, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - "The Line Forms Here," galley proofs, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - "On the Edge of Texas," research file, maps, correspondence, 1982, undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - "On the Edge of Texas," maps, undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - "On the Edge of Texas," drafts, edited galley proofs, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - "Governor's New Clothes," research notes, 1980-1981, undated (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - "Governor's New Clothes," drafts (handwritten and typed) and published article in Texas Monthly, May 1981 (Box 13, Folder 7)
      - "What Texas Means to Me," research notes and drafts, undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - "Isle Without End," notes, undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - "On the Set of Lonesome Dove," research material, call sheets from the set, drafts, galley proofs, 1988, undated (Box 14, Folder 3)
      - "The Lost Tribe," notes, drafts, galley proofs, undated (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Texas Monthly 20th Anniversary Issue, 1992, undated
      - Correspondence, drafts, and galleys, 1992, undated (Box 31, Folder 4)
      - Various drafts and galleys with Harrigan's annotations, 1992, undated (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - Texas Monthly Magazines, 1979-1981, 1988
      - January, July, and August 1979 (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - January, June, and August 1980 (Box 15, Folder 1)
      - October and November 1980 (Box 15, Folder 2)
      - February and April 1981 (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - May and August 1981 (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Correspondence and artwork, 1980, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - General Works, 1976-1988, undated
    - Various untitled drafts, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Application for NASA's Journalist in Space Program (1986), memo from Texas Commission of Arts (1981), and interview with Harrigan by Mark Gozonsky in West Austin News (1988), 1981, 1986, 1988 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Notebook, Poetry, 1976 (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Notebook, Prose, 1978 (Box 31, Folder 7)
- Correspondence, 1976-1991, undated
  Within this series is correspondence relating to Harrigan's writing. The letters range from requests for articles from magazines and journals to letters of interest from agents and publishers, "Letters to the Editor" forwarded to Harrigan from Texas Monthly, letters from other writers and friends, fan mail, and correspondence from organizations like the Texas Institute of Letters, of which Harrigan is a former president. The series is arranged chronologically except for one folder of short notes from Lee Goerner, Harrigan's editor at Knopf. Other correspondents of note include John A. Sterling, Wallace Stegner, A.C. Greene, Elmer Kelton and Gunnar M. Hansen.
  - Lee Goerner and Alfred A. Knopf, Inc., includes royalty statements and contract, 1978, 1984-1985, undated (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - International Creative Management and Texas State Library, 1980, 1983-1985, undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - Simon and Schuster Publishing, includes publishing agreement, 1983-1984, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence - contacts include Marge Harrigan, Justin Green, John Deaton, the University of Texas, Julian Bach Literary Agency, the University of Iowa, Houghton Mifflin Publishing, John A. Sterling, Paul R. Reynolds, Bill Broyles, and fan mail, 1976-1980, undated (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence - contacts include James P. Hart, Albert C. Lewis, Outside magazine, Houston City Magazine, Texas Institute of Letters, PEN: An Association of Writers, Esquire, Simon and Schuster Publishing, and others, 1981-1988 (Box 16, Folder 7)
- Personal Materials, undated
  Within this series are a few materials relating to Harrigan's personal life. Of particular interest are swimming fins and underwater slate, still imprinted with faint notes from a scuba diving trip.
  - Personal Materials, includes underwater slate used during the writing of Water and Light, notes, etc., undated (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - Swimming fins (Box 33)
- Works By Others, 1971-1993, undated
  This series contains the typescripts of one screenplay and two books by writers other than Harrigan. Arrangement is alphabetical by author.
  - Raven's Bride by Elizabeth Crook, three audio-tapes (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - "Texas Ramblers," an original screenplay by Ken Harrison, draft, November 1982 (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Texas, by James A. Michener, photocopy of edited draft (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
  - Barton Springs Eternal: The Soul of a City, Essays, Photos, and Oral History, edited by Turk Pipkin and Marshall Frech, photocopy and correspondence, 1992-1993, undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - "The Snake Doctors," poem by Frank Stanford (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - From Hell to Breakfast, book of poetry by James Whitaker (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - 100 Flowers, literary journal, Spring 1971 (Box 32, Folder 1)
- Texas Institute of Letters, 1982-1986
  This series contains material from Harrigan's years as an active member of the Texas Institute of letters. The documents include meeting minutes, financial statements, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and programs from Institute events
  - Clippings, correspondence, meeting minutes, and programs, 1982-1983 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, correspondence, financial documents, newsletters, programs, 1985-1986 (Box 32, Folder 3)
- Clippings, 1971-1983
  This series includes photocopies of newspaper clippings about Harrigan and his work saved by the author and original clippings of his ads for the University Co-op. His Co-op ads have been preservation photocopied and reside in Series I.
  - Clippings about Harrigan, 1977-1983 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Original clippings of Co-op ads, preservation photocopies can be found in Series I. (Box 34, Box 35)